um hi I don't normally do introductions
in my videos but I think on this
occasion is warranted for a couple of
reasons firstly I need to provide a
little bit of context for anyone that is
not already familiar with Jordan Hall
and Daniel smacking Berger and the rest
of the neuro hacker collectives work and
and others along similar lines so I need
to read just a little bit of context if
you have not already I highly recommend
you watch these two videos the paradox
of the times and the three-way
conversation between Jordan Hall Daniels
Martin burger and Jamie will that'll
give you a pretty good background to the
ideas that we're going to discuss here
this really does follow on from that but
if you're not going to take the four
hours or whatever to fill yourself in
with that I do need to provide just a
little bit of context as to what this
conversation is about and so Jordan and
his colleagues they make the case that's
the only way to actually tackle tackle
and handle the challenges and problems
that are facing and coming our way off
is through the creation of effective
decentralized collective intelligence
large numbers of people collaborating in
non-rivalry ways in order to interface
with and find solutions to the highly
complex problems that faces key to that
process is the ability to discern in
communications between people the wheat
from the chaff or signal from the noise
as they would put it and so the ability
to home in directly in immediately on
what is a value and it's kind of ignored
is not is is crucial to the whole
process of the decentralized collective
intelligence and it is that idea of
determine how to build discernment what
discernment is and how to go about
building it that we're going to be
exploring in more detail in this video
the other thing I would like to say is
that I had a technical breakdown about
10 minutes in something like that I had
a technical breakdown and it took about
10 minutes or so for me to get myself
organized and get back on another
computer and so not only is there a
drop-off in video quality at my end
Jordans fine but at my end as a sphere
drop-off in video quality but also I'd
just like to say publicly that you know
Jordan just hung around and waited for
me a guy he doesn't know with a channel
you know very few subscribe
very little exposure and so I think it
speaks to his authenticity and
willingness to you know just talk to
people that he thinks you know the right
time has to come to talk about a certain
thing which I'm pretty sure why he's
agreed to talk to me so yeah I think
that's all I really want to say and I'll
run the interview from now so thank you
very much for watching I hope you enjoy
it not entirely sure why he agreed to
talk to me but I'm very very grateful
that you have the question is stop this
actually always a the mystery for me so
I I have found myself over the past gosh
I guess actually five years um what's
really putting this so what you do when
you feel it and you don't when you don't
yeah and in many ways I actually also am
noticing when things show up so I don't
I did quite significantly in tend not to
have a strategy I'm particular thing
that you call a marketing strategy right
so I don't if I if I feel even if I
feeling myself a noticing that there's a
certain um we may put it almost like a
sociopathic her non-human potential or
like I can I could benefit from this
conversation yeah you'll avoid it on
that basis like if that if that's the
vibe you feeling you'll you'll avoid it
or you'll treat it with care or at least
I'll treat it with care is that a better
way of putting it yeah and then and not
I'm not familiar with any circumstance
in this milieu like a conversation that
is being recorded that may eventually at
some point be shared have I proactively
reached out to anyone right there are a
couple of areas that I'd particularly
like so hear more from you about and I
think I lay all of this out at the start
rather than ask you a question get an
answer ask you another question getting
other ants right now sort of all of the
areas that I'm interested in and
exploring with you start and then within
the conversation that we have you can
when it feels like a good time to
touch on one of those things you can
then choose to touch on at the end you
see what I mean right and that's the
first one as I mentioned in the email to
you is discernment I mean I've heard you
say this is foundational to the whole
thing right is the ability to is the
ability to discern well and so I would
like to explore more what tools we have
available to us as individuals for
discernment how reliable are those tools
what are the most effective ways of
honing those tools and what are good
indicators that we are doing discernment
well what what what kinds of things make
good indicator that we are doing
discernment well also traps I mean I've
just listened to another thing on rebel
wisdom Rosalyn
no sorry Bonita Roy Bernie - Roy and it
was really a you're nodding your VC Cena
and and she was talking about this that
you know we are tackling problems gamei
problems in your frame which tackling
gameid problems and all we have at our
disposal at the moment is game a code
and we may run it in a way that feels
different and like we're doing something
different but actually it's the only
tool at our disposal and so one of the
biggest traps I see with discernment is
using game a structures game a
architecture to discern and it'll be so
easy to fool ourselves because we've
we've come across a cool new idea right
there
that we're not actually just I'm not
showing I'm not sure I'm putting this
all that clearly but we're not just
actually running the same routines that
we were always running but maybe things
like end of Terry who said yeah and by a
confirmation of bias I think he's going
to feel pretty good that might feel like
the signal that you're trying to home in
on when it's not actually it's
masquerading as signal so these kinds of
traps I would like to explore what you
think about all the what you think about
these traps and ways are possibly
avoiding them
I imagine to be perfectly frank that
will be all the time we'll have that's
absolutely fine I want to do it properly
as well so and let's not clutter up your
head with too much other crap as well
right
exactly I was feeling I'm spooling out
space to try to hold the whole thing and
then I was like wow okay this is already
quite expensive and and I think we can
actually get a lot of interesting stuff
done I like a whole lot about the lift
of timing I think now is the time with
this cut this particular point is very
important and maybe is uh like in the
sweet spot people are contemplating it
in a place where they could actually
something useful could happen okay so
discernment may be the first thing for
me to put out there is I'm actually I
think the way to look at the what I'm
about to say is to recognize that I
myself am somewhere in say 33 to 50
percent in discernment right so I am I'm
very much in the process of building
capacity and even building sensitivity
to the essence of what it is so in some
sense there's a negative to that because
I'm speaking without a great deal of
embodied wisdom and experience so but on
the other side my edges are edgy my
associate yeah and they knew in my
freshman yeah yeah that's really yeah
you'll think you barely stuff all the
time right I'm thinking about this stuff
all the time
yeah I'm definitely spending a lot of
time contemplating it I'm looking at
quite diverse ways of looking at it and
I think that's one of the things I I
tend to do is not go down one path but
actually try multiple distinct and often
paths that don't communicate with each
other and I've been aware of each other
and try to see what would that higher
perspective gives so so in this case
what I think might be a really good way
of doing it is actually trying to frame
it in a very that's right we're putting
a very naturalistic way so I want to
talk about discernment or to me of maybe
it's the simplest and clearest ways to
talk about it in a fashion that is
leaning more in the direction of say
cognitive neuroscience that's a very
naturalistic nature and here
I mean her fakies stuff is like a really
good bone broth it's just rich in this
stuff but he has a nice stack where he
stacked different ways of known he has
participatory knowing and then he has
perspect I will note he has two more
proposition of them at the top but if we
just focus on participant Victorian
perspective which also map to things
like relevance realization yeah and
salience landscaping I'd like to do is
try to actually ground discernment in
things that are very simple because
oftentimes in this world we can have
frankly pretty esoteric words and I
think this sort of determinism to action
that esoteric I mean at a certain point
you can get there but let's start
rounded so we can begin with just the
notion of the body and perception and we
might say that discernment is the
increasingly skillful capacity to
perceive what is really happening to
perceive simply what really is with both
precision and subtlety and okay so when
we're talking about that we're talking
about perception and in the context of
perception we can begin to tease apart
what are the different aspects of
perception both in terms of what
supports it and what gets in the way
yeah and in terms of what supports it
again we can be very simple who gets
thought to talk about for example
discernment in terms of just being able
to see with our eyes and if you have a
child an infant in the beginning as an
if it is born their capacity to perceive
with their eyes is that fact quite look
they can only focus a couple of inches
in fact they can't control the movement
of their eyes so discernment with eyes
look as you mature your capacity to
focus properly your ability to actually
identify colors and be able to actually
literally at a neurological level map
the way the rods and the cones are being
stimulated by different wavelengths of
light to particular qualia is the
process of discernment and so you can
actually proceed
there is a face in front of you and that
his mom and you can actually have that
level of precision nuance your ability
to make sense of the word of the world
through your visual senses is taught to
you if you like while you know it you
should acquire membership in the
collectively agreed ways of perceiving
the world right and so you're the
development of your visual sense is as
much a cultural phenomenon as a
biological phenomenon right or at least
they are they're they're they're they're
sort of elements of business it's honest
I wouldn't see it as much I would say
that in in the context of other things
that have a much larger like the name of
the color that you see yeah quickly
cultural the fact that you are
distinguishing colors is much more
biological and so this is this like
something happening this I think is the
key is discernment has this connection
through the entire arc of evolution
right so if you want to run it back from
your eyes go back back back back back to
like the beginning of the ability of
biological organism to have photonic
sensitivity at all I think that are
distinguished from light and dark in
some physical way that is reliable and
then the degree to which that capacity
because it has some fitness advantage
presumably becomes up regulated there's
an increasing ability which eventually
becomes the specialization of particular
cells that are photosensitive and then
the dural of differentiation of this
particular cells to be more particularly
photosensitive until eventually get the
development of things like eyes and the
visual cortex right so and there's a
there's a continuity there there's
actually in me in in my visual field
there's actually a connection all the
way back down to that very beginning
moment of the of utility and perhaps in
this case the stochastic were or random
notion of distinguishing these two
characteristics which actually predate
visual field of course because obviously
under the hot sun simply being the
presence of photons is kinetic I can
okay it can actually kill me just by
regardless of whether my can distinguish
its presence and that I think it's kind
of a good way of grasping is to remember
that discernment is very grounded it
goes all the way down as far down as you
care to examine it in
becoming nosov physical reality and a
big part of this again this idea of
participatory knowing is at the bottom
discernment is really about the degree
to which you are part of the context
you're not separate from it you are of
it yeah there is a continuity between
you and world that is deeply deeply
connected in many many different end and
interconnected and subtle ways so then I
have this one level higher so let's say
I with my visual field I perceive some
object in the world in front of it but
of course it may be a hallucination
maybe a visual hallucination
it's okay neat so I had this notion I
just added a whole concept which is the
possibility not just of call it richness
precision and nuance in my visual fields
for my ability to distinguish between
red and blue and also my abilities now
distinguish between red and orange and
then red and Rose right that that that
level of nuance and precision but now I
have the concept of actual error where I
think I see the color red but I don't
actually have some other artifacts
something else is producing that so but
of course now what I have is I have a
multimodal possibility I can reach out
with my hand towards that thing that my
eyes see and using a completely
different mode of perception and now
it's touch or smell or hearing and
attempt to verify whatever right now and
if I do but my hand goes right through
it what happens is that I actually have
my capacity to perceive what is really
happening goes way up
oh I'm actually not seeing a real red
object instead there's something else
that I'll categorize as a hallucination
or a you know my daughter is ten months
we have a prism so she'll see a red
light on the wall doesn't fit doesn't
fit in your paradigm right whatever it
is doesn't ever it is it doesn't fit
your paradigm exactly so now I'm at
least in a novel space and I have a
there's something about what I thought I
saw isn't there and let's hold that
piece because this recursion between
what you are perceiving in its most raw
sense and what you perceive that you
perceive in its sense making sense I
think is exactly the point
we're just cermets it's is right between
those
so we had this continual movement of a
training a development of capacity in
modes of perception in an ability to
achieve reliability and precision and
subtlety and then in expanding these
modes of perception each one of which
has brings his own characteristic a
passage to perceive and the complex of
which increases the overall capacity for
discernment and here's where I would
point out that if we go back to the
notion of the body there's a very large
number of these modes of perception if
there's not enough six senses there's
many thousands maybe hundreds of
thousands from harm to know some are
very very interior there really are
nuanced ways of actually discerning say
for example the way that your stomach is
responding to the experience that you're
having and you can feel that if you
point if you notice that you can feel it
your your tests contracts like muscles
you can actually feel the sensation of
the change of your breathing and there's
something going on there's some signal
that is contained in this subtle nuance
because again this goes all the way down
the evolutionary arc where billions of
years of life endeavoring to more fully
and accurately and precisely didn't
suddenly perceive what is real so as to
be able to make better choices in the
context the whole shebang though right
it's every single one of those thousands
of very very subtle messages going on in
your body all at the same time right and
at the same time yeah and so I mean it
is it is impossible obviously to be
aware of each and every one of those on
an individual basis in any given moment
right and so right that's the symphony
you're listening to the symphony you
can't necessarily pick out the
instruments but you but you're aware of
the symphony is that a reasonable
analogy is that yeah yeah so now now we
have another concept we can put in the
concept here is called feelings and here
I want I want to disambiguate emotions
from feeling feelings yeah yeah yeah and
I wanna I want to we support feelings
for being something that is one of the
more powerful instruments in discernment
so the feeling I'd like to point to is
the feeling of balance so you're
standing do you feel balanced or not
you're standing on one foot I noticed
you can actually tell that there's a
real concept that real
oh yes there's a feeling a sensation of
balance that I can notice and by the way
it's extremely effective like if I'm
standing on one foot and I'm on a
platform for example it's a mistress to
move the platform you yeah I don't know
that's happening I feel the lack of
balance now think about that in the
countries what you just said what's
actually happening is I'm getting
probably several thousand distinct
feedbacks from my muscular system and
from different aspects of my
proprioceptive systems that are actually
I can't be aware of and frankly any one
or two of them but the pathetic
integration of all of them together in a
singular quality that I can be aware of
known as the feeling of balance is that
thing and that's that's the coherent
entity right is the feeling of balance
yeah that's so a feeling is a coherent
entity in relationship to a potentially
extraordinarily vast number of distinct
perceptions that are synthetically
integrated into something that provides
a qualitative sense of and it's a very
it's a very and that's the that's the
participate or II knowing right I mean
that you you you know that for sure in
yourself how you feel there's no right
yeah right and so the the capacity to
develop or refining and developing
discernment is very much that capacity
to be more and more aware of and
sensitive to the complex of feelings
that are rising then being able to
actually use them moment to moment in
making the choices that you make and
again we can make this very simple if
you're doing gymnastics or martial arts
or very embodied actions skateboarding
you'll notice that like the process of
learning how to ollie and in the process
of learning how to go from Ollie to to a
kickflip is a it's a feeling and it's a
way of actually using and linking
together a series of feelings each one
which is basically just saying yes or
rightness and with extremely fine tune
subtle mood shifts in very specific
context right have you ever seen
somebody do a kickflip it's a little bit
mind-blowing that it's possible at all
and yet after a bit of practice the body
can do that and the same
is true across the entire spectrum of
human activities okay so now anchoring
it very deeply in that evolutionary
story and the groundedness and in the
body now it's moved to the place that
ends up being a lot of trouble and a lot
of trouble is the things that get in
between us and discernment yeah and this
is largely places where we have
projections and/or we have knowing or
schema I don't understand tensions as
well right
that's very good let's see what we say
how would we say that very cleanly yes
that would actually be something like I
would say in my sense something like
lack of integrity or lack of congruence
yeah where in your own self there may
actually multiple distinct processes
that are running and
that's actually the whole category where
if you don't if you're not sensitive to
the degree to which you are an agent in
your own perception yeah then that
agency can very much mutter the waters
can very much get in the way you might
say something to me and that I might
respond in a certain way perhaps even a
certain tone comes out of my voice and
that's because some part of me heard
felt thought it heard didn't it was
coming from a different place that put
an energy or a quality of say
defensiveness or a quality of
protectiveness and just kind of injected
it into the complex of expression
because expression is as subtle complex
and nuanced as perception right both
directions and and even if there was no
such tone coming from your end that
doesn't stop me perceiving such as her
even was intended exactly and so they're
all true and of course here's that whole
thing of like microaggressions because
there's certainly thing as
micro-expressions and the reality is
that my body is processing a very large
number of things all at the same time
right even as I'm in presence is
speaking with you there are things going
on in the back of my mind bitter
recalling you know my conversations my
wife considering my daughter the
cleanness is going on in the future the
more capable I am of being present here
the less I'm bringing into this
interaction that creates noise at the
more it's the what's happening is real
this is crucial like with the idea of
being present I think it's very much
that and the more I'm elsewhere the more
I'm bringing in things that are actually
going to generate noise in our
relationship in our conversation the
more I'm present the more what I am
generating when I'm expressing and what
I'm perceiving is part of what's
happening here in this moment and so to
kind of tag that presence and
discernment are very closely linked
where present you are the less you're
creating or perceiving noise in what is
really happening I mean a tension is
also a function of presence right I know
you you can't be attentive without being
present right as part of the same thing
giving your attention giving your
concentration giving your full listening
capaz
see - this is all these are all
components of presents right yeah I mean
to be very precise it's you can't pay
attention to what is happening here
without being present your attention is
going to be by definition elsewhere and
that's I think was where you were saying
yeah and so we've got a lot of
interesting staff right there so the
degree to which I'm not present which
that means my attention is elsewhere
there's the degree to which by but the
fact that I'm not president I'm
simultaneously
mixing where my attention is elsewhere
with what I'm perceiving here which can
be very confusing and quite likely
bringing in the influences that
elsewhere into what I'm presenting here
which can be quite confusing so let's
say now let's get that out of the way
let's say I'm actually doing pretty good
job being present and let's say for
example I'm actually doing a pretty good
job of being aware sensitive to what's
going on notice that at least in my
experience this requires a bit of
slowing down
the more you speed up with less likely
you'll have the ability to kind of allow
the it's a pace of processing in your
body to show up in your experience and
yet all tendencies to do the exact
opposite right when we feel nervous when
we feel under pressure when we feel
uncertain we tend to rush through it
because it's uncomfortable right I'll
tendency is to do the exact opposite of
that I think yes and that notion of
avoidance seems like it's pretty
fundamental to getting under way of
discernment and so in my experience in
particular
learning how to convert avoidance into
curiosity mm-hmm is a pretty powerful
alchemical move okay would you be able
to point to a type of practice that
might engender that sort of change but I
think I agree with you I think that's
important air turning turning
uncertainty in security I think that's I
think that's a really important one I
like that yeah well one is was is the
the degree to which you can actually do
things by intent so what is being
conscious of the intent and then
oftentimes actually setting the intense
thanks getting it out loud actually
helps or writing it down setting the
intent explicitly now of course you can
have simple practices so simplifying
simplifying is a good way to hone these
kinds of very specific things so
meditation practice for exam always
almost any things that don't involve
body movement if you're trying to do
dancing meditation may get in the way a
little bit
but meditating first and then doing
games down yeah so in this case you can
then say listen let's identify something
that I I'm pretty sure I have a an
avoidance behavior around you know some
rough part of my emotional development
you know some relationship that's tough
some some piece of myself that I know
that I don't feel I feel shame about
mm-hm and then in your meditation
practice and intentionally point your
attention towards that and then in the
in the context of your meditation
practice you now have the capacity to
move very slowly and notice wearing your
body for example the avoidance shows up
and you can notice when that avoidance
in your body happens what happens in
your mind you just slow it down slow
down the film and terror actually
aimless see it was real precision what
these things are and you know my
experience at least as a human is that
I've got a lot of these lots and lots
and lots of things that are
characteristic of avoidance behavior and
so it's not hard for me to practice just
on my own interior and then what I
it's also then is as I've built some
time in that and this and take actually
that long look in the order of say three
to six months so the habits can begin to
be built where the the attentional
structure the relevance realization
machinery is beginning to be trained
they can't help but when the body
responds in a certain way to go oh wait
a minute
yeah in that before what's that alright
so then if you're in in life as you're
experiencing things somebody does or
says something and now that that habit
of being attentive begins to actually
come up as opposed to just become
unconscious and unconscious avoidance
behavior kicks in yeah isn't it is
usually unconscious you just do it you
don't even realize that you've done it
and so you continue to avoid the same
things yeah no I like that a lot so as
you start to bring it into awareness you
start to create I don't know like a more
generally used pathway that can then
start to bring other ones that you
hadn't been aware of before we now start
to become aware of them because the
light gets brighter you can shine it on
more things right yeah bad it's just
think about the eyeball exactly pick
about the eyeball and then what you'd
like to do she acts like to get some
winds you'd like to get the body to have
that signal of that was actually a good
use of time mmm so to the degree to
which you can find yourself actually
upgrading a habit or resolving a problem
like you know in this in this case in my
in my experience you're more meaningful
relationships or very good places you
know if you if you notice that by virtue
of pointing your attention to something
we've got an avoidance behavior and by
putting your attention at that in like a
meditation practice you can become more
and more nerds towards it you can then
if you find that by doing that in say in
a relationship with your spouse for
example when something comes up that you
would have previously unconsciously
avoided you don't avoid it and as a
result something quite meaningful happen
so it may not necessarily be happy
immediately but it it shifts something
in the relationships that the
relationship is stronger it's richer
it's more nuanced then what you can do
is you can actually remove that in this
by the way as neuro hacking by the way
you can loop that in a meditation
practice or any other practices with a
gratitude practice
so the next time that you're focusing on
this particular avoidance you can then
give yourself the win
you can like okay now what I'm going to
do is I'm really going to focus on that
fact that I really do believe that I did
something that increase the
meaningfulness of this most meaningful
relationship and actually and I myself
to feel good about it yeah yeah exactly
thank you for doing such a good job
thank you for working so hard on getting
better at being able to be in
relationships that matter and that's
great right so now you're actually
giving that that roared in in deeply
it's a deep reward it's not it's not an
extrinsic override and so you're
training yourself to have better habits
at becoming at converting avoidance into
noticing and converting noticing into
curiosity and that's a big piece of a
lot of work that's not trivial and so
that's but it's course trafficking
because once you've got that course
scaffolding in place you'll be able to
find yourself when something comes up it
feels quite wrong instead of shutting it
down or avoiding it which the two sort
of habitual responses you actually find
yourself in if stage yeah uh-huh okay
which has happened to you that's
interesting and curiosity is not
necessarily or not at all foolishness
you could be aware of a wrongness and
you may choose to actually avoid it like
no no that actually is in fact wrong huh
that's what the head what's happening
where here's not not a good thing that
me skillfully this is discernment right
discernment has this characteristic of
choosing what you relate with and how
you relate with it okay once you can
perceive it clearly proceed what is real
clearly then you're empowered to
actually choose effectively how you want
to be in relationship with it so just
serving kind of includes a little bit of
both more from my mind on the perception
side but frankly I may just be early in
the process of getting it from the
choice of truth choosing side but until
you know until you have clarity of
perception your ability to just separate
let's just use it again simple taste so
I take something I don't know what it is
and I bite it and it
terrible I can choose not to eat it
anymore I have I'm using a really nice
high quality perception and using that
to inform better choices I can choose my
relationality more effectively that
conscious avoidance in full knowledge of
what you're doing is not the avoidance
that we're talking about yeah exactly
exactly and so then and we only have
just a few minutes but just enough I
think and so then the last little piece
here is the very cognitive I so now are
like in the place of the very the mental
and here's where we have when we talked
about shutting down which we didn't talk
about a lot but shutting down an
avoidance or to things that that are
getting away projection mmm-hmm lack of
presence and and here what I want to do
is I want to talk about the the deeply
cognitive and perhaps quite specifically
prefrontal cortex and Broca's area the
linguistic stuff where
you import an entire schema of
what is into a perception so
I perceive
and here's lots I perceive you you have
a shape to your face you have a color to
your skin you have a turn to your voice
you have a context this behind you and
of course I cannot help but be making a
very large number of assumptions you
know expanding that to provide more and
more context than we have a sense of
what relationality is but those
assumptions or assumptions right there's
what I am perceiving so for example
here's a very simple one I don't
actually know for sure that there's a
back to your head yeah right yeah I have
a very nice high quality eristic that
there probably is and I will assume
under almost all circumstances there is
but I don't know for sure in fact to be
perfectly frank I didn't know for sure
you're a real human you may be amazingly
effective AI deep faith yeah so there's
a noticing at what actually is really
what I'm perceiving and then an ability
to notice what am i projecting onto that
perceiving to create context to support
my capacity to make choices at all and
note and B wow that's a lot there's a
whole lot that I'm I'm projecting on in
that context and that's okay because I
can't do crap would unless I can do that
but then to just be aware of that
distinction and even to have a certain
in my mind almost like a topography a
topographical map of what's really
really dense at the center like the
notion that you have a three-dimensional
body is the kind of heuristic that I'm
willing to make up Linden
yeah on that but the notion that you
have malevolent intent because you have
an English accent and that reminds me of
bad guys in movies probably not the best
thing to to import as a heuristic right
and there's a lot of that and so then
you have a whole bunch of loops you know
loops and loops and loops where there's
a combination of the possibility that I
may be importing things into what is
here that are in fact not really here
I'm just importing them and then I could
be reacting to my own importance yeah
with a variety of different
physiological responses and if I'm not
noticing my own physiological response
like I may for example you may say
something some phrase and that phrase
may mean something to you it may mean
something different to me because of our
for quite different context so I'm I'm
importing a huge schema of what that
means
means something to me which is quite
Hospital and so now I find that my body
is responding with a kind of a
contraction and an arousal I'm getting
ready to fight and I'm moving away from
the antidote to this then is is that
when you notice that coming up in
yourself you clarify with your
interlocutor whatever it is that may be
troubling and what was the remedy to
this yea well then remember that those
habits so have one habit as a habit of
pace slow down another habit is a habit
of awareness listen closely listen to
the nuance the body can be quite nuanced
so even if you've got one portion of
your body is retracting other portions
of your body might not be remember eyes
and hands and ears to get a better sense
of what is real if a small part of me is
actually recoiling from what happened
but the remainder of me is it then I'm
like okay that's interesting that tells
me a lot about what I'm perceiving let
me slow down more the ability to
distinguish between what is real what is
really perceived what is really
happening and what is important which
may involve more slowing down yeah I was
going to say that that seems that
strikes me as being an extremely
difficult thing to do with any degree of
assuredness or accuracy because as you
said right at the start of your point we
import a whole bunch of stuff and as we
get to know the person better we discard
some of the stuff that we initially
imported and we replace it with stuff
which we have actually lied about right
but in that I think it's very I mean I
maybe I'm just not particularly
self-aware but I think that would be
extremely difficult to know with any
certainty where the boundary between
what you actually know about a person
will even brought about them it really
is I spend a lot of time with my wife
and we've been together for a while
we've been through a lot of stuff mmm
still continuously surprised but I don't
really know who she is
so that's that's yeah yet at the same
time the body and experience has a lot
of wisdom to it and fortunately going
back to this notion of evolution
humans are naturally band organisms and
we naturally show up in groups and and
that evolved over a very long period of
time at the notion of social animal is
very old and on the basis of social
animal you build more and more and more
construction so this instrument is
actually remarkably effective at knowing
what's really happened you've done this
something called a family constellation
no yeah it's really neat practice where
you could get a group of strangers
together let's say you spend three days
together in some activity it could be
anything it could be camping in the
woods you could be in a you know some
kind of workshop doesn't really matter
and then we can do is you can actually
ask one of them to be the center of a
family constellation so think like solar
system the stress was playing the role
of the Sun and their job is without
using any words just by physically
grabbing people and moving them to
orient people in space and in
orientation around them at the center so
you might stand the centrum kind of feel
and then kind of grab me and me here and
turn me and they go back to the center
and see them and grab this person and
move them a little bit and like very
corpse like it's literally just spatial
orientation distance and left-right in
rotation is sometimes up-down by the way
sometimes even a little bit of motion
and then we can happen is it's a you go
to that whole process is all silent and
then you go through you ask each person
in order what their perception of what
was happening was the first thing you'll
notice is that it's shockingly accurate
but by the way not necessarily
third-person so if you and Bob you've
moved Bob somewhere you and Bob will
quite likely have a very similar sense
of what was happening there I may not
have any idea I may be quite wrong what
I thought was happening between you and
Bob right and also so the next is you
could say okay now everybody shift to
where you think is more rightness for
using those feeling systems where's a
more rightness and what I noticed at
least in doing this is that on the one
hand everybody shifts another the head
everybody shifts just a little bit and
then
finally and it actually does feel better
so everybody has the capacity to notice
what is the right actual orientation the
right relationship this is because we're
running social mammal machinery which is
really old really robust honed over
millions of years and its really good at
knowing that and it's knowing what's the
right orientation and by the way it's
been watching for three days in this
hypothesis and tracking all the stuff
deeply deeply deeply deeply so yes the
the degree to which you can run in
conscious awareness in this tiny tiny
little window of attention that we focus
that we can actually call conscious
attention the dimension can run this
kind of discernment there is miniscule
but the degree that you can run it on
top of this whole scaffolding remarkably
nuanced okay the house I guess how do we
get out of our own way and then allow
that to happen then I guess that's
that's the key isn't it that's the key
yeah and that's practice you know
practice practice and practice both in
yourself and just learning how to move
yourself into dispositions of curiosity
practice learning how to have real right
relationship with your own feeling
systems and practice that even you know
again physicality practice learning how
to taste tastes and smell smells to
distinguish sounds are just tuning the
basic raw components practice putting
yourself in circumstances where you're
really afraid and where you're really
excited and you can feel how that
creates a different sort of set of
ripples in your interior and then in
life just notice where your discernment
seems to have shown up accurately it's
given you good precise subtle
perspective of what's happening and
notice where it has it and just
recognize that you're gonna be a lot
wrong and you might be a little more
right and as you do it more and more you
can be more and more confident but never
fully got me wide awake and super aware
all the time ever new all the time all
the time wide awake and super where it's
not easy it's not easy not easy no but
it does become less effortful right yeah
yes go back to our skateboarder like a
kickflip saw seriously a hard thing to
do but once you've done it enough your
body has it and it takes care of that or
to be more common riding a bike yeah
when you're six five four when you're
first riding a bike that's really hard
it's scary
and you can crash but once you've
actually practiced it enough this system
can actually integrate it integrated
integrate it and render it into the
autonomic that makes it now a baseline
upon which you can do other skills so
good discernment can become autonomic
you'll say in fact you want it to be
don't you that's the whole point you
want to get you Oh reason out the way
you want it to be that's the whole point
yeah and then you could allow reason to
be on top of something that it's a solid
foundation yeah really the ability to
say okay now maybe I'm actually dealing
with cause different cognitive biases
let me be thoughtful about them kind of
run some questions and how can i tree
ain't triangulate so there's again a
sort of a right relationship you get the
participatory knowing solid and really
clear and clean and well-functioning
then the propositional knowing actually
could do its work well not perfectly
because you know all kinds of things
going on but well I meant unfortunately
this is the end time I had for this
conversation no problem
his schedules having another one I'd
really like to because I mean yeah I'd
like I'd look forward to another call
great nice one thanks very much Jordan
appreciate it